foreign
[Music]
healthy plant-based diets have been
associated with lower all-cause
mortality up to a 34 lower risk of death
from any cause over an average of an
eight-year period just being the top
versus bottom quarter of healthy
plant-based consumption if sustained
that could translate into more than four
extra years of life a meta-analysis of a
dozen studies prospectively following
more than half a million people for up
to 25 years simply found significantly
lower heart disease and overall death
rates among those eating more
plant-based no surprise a systematic
review concluded since plant-based diets
May arrest or even reverse our number
one killer cardiovascular disease those
eating wholly plant-based tend to be
significantly Slimmer with lower LDL
cholesterol triglycerides blood sugars
blood pressure significantly less
inflammation and less carotid artery
wall thickening a sign of
atherosclerosis measured via ultrasound
in the neck as good as what you see in
endurance athletes who've run an average
of 50
000 miles which is like twice around the
globe
and changes in risk factors can happen
fast as evidenced by results from one to
three week ad libidum eat all you want
plant-based Kickstart programs for
example the results from the first few
hundred participants of the at-home 15
day Jump Start program created by the
nonprofit Rochester lifestyle medicine
Institute were recently published on a
whole food plant-based diet obese
patience lost an average of seven pounds
without controlling portions or counting
calories or carbs diabetics saw their
fasting blood sugars drop 28 points
those with LDL cholesterol over 100
experienced a 33 Point drop comparable
to some statin drugs and hypertensive
individuals experienced the 17 point
drop in systolic blood pressure which is
better than drugs and all within just
two weeks
studies dating back nearly 40 years show
those eating meat-free diets also have
improved blood rheology meaning fluidity
or flow ability which may play a wrong
cardiovascular protection subsequent
Interventional studies putting the
cross-sectional findings to the test
show that switching people to a
plant-based diet can improve rheology
measurements within three to six weeks
but might the blood of vegetarians flow
a bit too well though in 2019 a study of
thousands of British vegetarians called
epic Oxford found that they were at a
higher risk of hemorrhagic or bleeding
stroke they had such a lower risk of
heart disease that they still had less
cardiovascular disease overall and half
dozen studies show no overall increased
risk of stroke mortality but why it's a
greater stroke incidence I suggest it
might be vitamin B12 deficiency which
can lead to excessive levels of a stroke
Associated metabolite called
homocysteine which is normally
detoxified by B12
this is thought to be the reason why
vitamin B12 supplementation can improve
artery function of vegetarians vitamin
B12 supplements or fortified foods are
critical for anyone eating plant-based
but my 12 part video series on
vegetarians and stroke risks triggered
by the 2019 publication was all in vain
it turns out vegetarians don't appear to
have higher stroke risk after all in
response to the Epic Oxford results
researchers around the world scramble to
see if the findings were merely a fluke
in 2020 UK biobank a massive study
following more than 400 000 volunteers
confirmed that vegetarians had lower
cardiovascular disease rates and
importantly no increased incidence of
stroke and two studies from Taiwan found
vegetarians had significantly lower risk
of stroke following tens of thousands of
vegetarians for up to 10 years they only
had about half the stroke risk compared
to non-vegetarians including a 64 lower
risk specifically of hemorrhagic stroke
by 2021 Harvard researchers had finished
and published their analysis of the 200
000 plus participants of the nurse's
health study the nurses health study 2
and the health professionals follow-up
study they too found no increased stroke
risk for vegetarians and indeed a
decreased risk of stroke among those
eating healthy plant-based diets our
meta-announces putting all the studies
together found that indeed the Epic
Oxford data appeared to be a fluke after
all finding if anything a lower risk of
stroke in a subgroup analysis
a 2022 systematic review concluded that
vegetarian and low Animal product diets
are associated with a significantly
lower risk of bleeding Strokes a
significantly low risk of clotting
strokes and a significant low risk of
total Strokes across the board
[Music]
thank you